"Why should we know this?"
Say you maybe when the teacher pulls out some old text that was written hundreds of years ago.
The question may initially seem reasonable, but you - even if it sounds strange - were not created when you were born.
You were born into a world that has been shaped by people who have thought and thought things for thousands of years.
It is very good.
Therefore, every person who is born does not have to reinvent the wheel and mobile phone, or come from the ground up how to build houses or bake bread.
It is already fixed.
By reading old texts we gain an understanding of the world around us.
We get smart fucking who knows things.
Those you listen to.
Some call it general education.
You can also see it as a way to avoid appearing as an idiot.
Literature history is the story of how different texts have changed society and how society has changed the way we write texts.
Thus, by learning about literary history, you automatically learn a lot about society and thus also about yourself.
You become one of those smart bastards - a one you listen to.
The written language has not always existed.
First, people just talked to each other and then they started writing down important things.
It was pretty short things you wrote down.
Name of a person who had died, how many horses you had or otherwise important to remember.
null
Actually, those eras go into each other.
And it is difficult to say exactly when an era starts and ends and when the next begins.
Right now we are living in a postmodern time, but in a hundred years people may think that our era should have a better name such as "Snapchatism" or "Instagramism".
But let's travel back in a small time machine.
Back to that first literary era.
And then we have to go back so far that not even Jesus had been born and no one had heard of Christianity or Islam.
At this time, people sat in Sweden and froze in small huts, chased animals and ate berries.
Nobody wrote anything at all.
The oldest attempts with us to carve small simple words on wooden pieces and later stones, it was done at about the same time as Jesus was born in Palestine, that is, when we began to count our time.
This era - the first era - it is called antiquity and takes place first in Greece and later in the Roman Empire, which was based on the city of Rome in Italy.
Down in Greece had come so much further in their development than we Swedes had done.
In Athens, people lived in a way that much more is similar to the way we live today.
They even had large cities with water pipes.
They had theaters and high school.
Yes, though a high school was not quite the same as today.
It was a place where you sports naked.
In Greece during ancient times, democracy arose - that is, the idea that people together can decide things.
It was a pretty cash democracy but it was better than what you had before.
In this democracy, only men had to decide things.
And not even all men, but only free men.
And a third of all people at this time were slaves.
They were not allowed to decide anything at all.
In ancient times, a lot of gods were believed.
This is called "polyteism".
The gods had a lot of different powers and if you teased a god it could go really bad.
They were not always so forgiving and understanding.
During ancient times, different kinds of texts were written and you wrote in three different genres.
A genre is the same as a certain type of literature.
You talk about genres with movies today too.
You know as comedy, action or drama.
In literature you have a slightly different division.
The three genres that existed in ancient times were "lyric" that are kind of the same as short poems.
He is known for two important texts: the Illiad and the Odyssey.
The first - Illiad - is about the war in Troja and hero Achilles.
They cheat into the city with the help of a huge wooden horse full of soldiers.
The other, the Odyssey, is about the hero Odysseus trying to get home from the war.
He annoys the sea god Poseidon by hurting his son who is a gigantic giant with just one eye - one so called cyclops.
Since Odysseus has annoyed Poseidon, he happens to be horrible storms and adventures at sea before finally getting home.
Another famous writer during ancient times was Sapfo.
She lived on an island called Lesbos and wrote love poems.
They were aimed at women and therefore many have thought that Sapfo might be a lesbian.
And maybe she was.
Or she just wrote about good looking girls anyway.
In general, it was not so stingy in antiquity with sexuality.
You could lie a little with who you wanted.
Society did not care if people were in love with any of their own gender or the other.
The next era is the Middle Ages.
It fell the young sphere in 500 and extends a thousand years ahead.
It has been named by the fact that it was a typical medium period - an average period.
A rather boring time between two good eras.
Although that is not really true.
There are a lot of fun things then too.
During the Middle Ages, Christianity has spread and the church had great power.
It takes a good bit into the Middle Ages before Christianity reaches Sweden.
During the Middle Ages, the plague spread in Europe.
It was a terrible infectious disease that was sometimes obliterated by entire cities.
One of the most famous writers of the Middle Ages was Dante Alighieri.
He wrote a book called "The Divine Comedy".
It's not very funny.
But it is about a person and the person's journey through the different floors of hell.
When you read it you realized that it was best to sharpen and follow Christianity.
Otherwise, you could get really bad.
At the end of the Middle Ages, there was another Italian writer named Giovanni Boccaccio.
Not pikachu.
Boccaccio.
He is said to have invented the short story - you know those short texts that you sometimes read and write in school.
Hans Decamerone is a short story collection that has a frame story.
By frame story you mean a story that makes the other texts fit into a whole.
The Fam Story in Decamerone is that a number of young people have moved away from the pest's Florence.
They settle in a large house and to get the time to go, they tell different stories to each other.
These short stories are quite often about sex and religion.
Not infrequently in combination.
In Iceland, a special kind of fairy tales were written at this time.
They did not resemble today's fairy tales with "Snipp Snapp snout so the story was over" and "it was once" and princes and princesses.
Instead, it was stiff stories about family feuds and revenge.
Here, honor was vital.
Worst culture of honor.
These were no stories for children.
One of the most famous Icelandic writers had the somewhat unhappy name Snorre.
We can laugh at that today.
After the Middle Ages, the Renaissance fell.
Renaissance means "rebirth".
It comes from the French "Renaitre".
What one wanted to be born again - it was antiquity.
It was thought that a lot of crap had been written during the Middle Ages.
A lot of boring lyrics about the church and a lot of sad knight stories.
Instead, they wanted to write like antiquity.
Exciting drama and beautiful lyric.
Now you came up with how to print texts and suddenly ideas and words could be spread in quantities.
Before, they had to write every new copy you wanted from a book.
A rather tough job that made books extremely unusual and valuable.
But now books began to become something that ordinary people could own.
During the Renaissance, Europeans discover the world-
Columbus discovers America (which he believes is India).
And also forget that one cannot discover something that someone else had already discovered,
that is, the Indians who lived there before and who did not understand why they would be called Indians
Just because some madman had been wrong on North America and India.
During the Renaissance there was a writer named Miguel de Cervantes.
He was a Spanish and wrote a story about the failed knight Don Quijote.
Cervante's story became incredibly popular and people laughed at the tragic failed hero
Who mixed up dragons and windmills and princesses and peasant girls.
Another writer during this time was William Shakespeare
Several films today are inspired by these texts.
Not least Romeo and Julia that follow a typical theme of unhappy love.
After the Renaissance came the enlightenment.
It is called the enlightenment because people became increasingly enlightened and began to think critically and independently.
They were tired of the church's power and thought that the only important thing was knowledge and reason.
In France, revolution was made and the head of the king.
The people would decide.
Important writers during the enlightenment were Rosseau who wrote a book about child rearing
And Voltaire who wrote a lot of angry lyrics where he attacked the church.
The romance emerged as a criticism that the brain had pushed away the heart of literature.
With the romance, the horror stories appeared.
Texts about vampires and monsters, but also love texts about the deep passion that breaks down all reason.
Goethe wrote a text about the young Werther who is so unfortunate in love that he kills himself.
Mary Shelly wrote the story of Frankenstein's monster and Bram Stoker wrote the story about Dracula.
The romance was a kind of criticism of enlightenment's boring factual world and realism became a criticism of the lack of anchoring of romance.
After realism comes modernism.
Important writers are Franz Kafka or James Joyce.
At this time, artists start painting paintings where things don't really look like things look.
You know Picasso and stuff like that.
Modernism is a kind of revolt against the boring fixation of realism in accuracy.
A writer named Hugo Ball dressed up in a star gossip and read incomprehensible poems
consisting of words that were no real words.
Nowadays you talk about something called postmodernism.
It is a kind of clip and paste time full of different texts and directions.
We live in the middle of this so we have a hard time understanding what it really is.
Postmodernism means that there are a lot of different truths and that it is difficult to know who to really listen to.